Guide to the Department of University Health, Division of Student Mental Hygiene, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Department of Health, Division of Student Mental Hygiene, Yale University, records
1926-1969
RU 109
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.5
The records consist of administrative records, correspondence, conference and committee proceedings, drafts of articles, financial records, personnel records, research files, reports, subject files, and statistical files documenting the activities and projects of the Division of Student Mental Hygiene, Department of University Health, Yale University. Among the projects documented are the "Survey of Mental Health Services in Colleges" by psychiatrist Alice F. Raymond, which studied the state of psychiatric services offered in universities and colleges in the northeastern United States; and war related projects, which studied the effects of military service on Yale and Harvard men and the identification and suitability of homosexuals, psychoneurotics, and psychopaths in the military. The bulk of the records originate from the administration of Clements Collard Fry.
Yale University. Dept. of University Health
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 35 (YRG 35), Records documenting Yale health services.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were transferred from the Health Services Center, 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research, with the exception of budget and payroll records, which are restricted until January 1, 2044.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in three series: I. Administrative Records, 1926-1969. II. General Files and Correspondence, 1926-1964. III. Project Files, 1929-1956.
Scope and Contents
The research strengths of these records include gay and lesbian studies, as the documents assembled within cover the medicalization and diagnosis of homosexualityas a psychological disturbance, and writings, reports (including division personnel reactions to the Kinsey Report), and comments on homosexuals engaged in military and other public service. Another potentially rich area exists for those who study the psychology of war. Correspondence in the Project Files tracks the department's efforts to aid and advise the selection of men for military service, particularly officer candidates; psychiatric rejections in military screening; projects with multiple government offices to track the military careers of previous Yale and Harvard psychiatric patients; and statistics on psychological trauma to deployed troops. Many of the findings of these projects may be found in published reports issued separately by the department or the U.S. military. More obvious directions for potential research include the historical administration of university psychiatric services, and context material for related published works such as the division's 1942 book Mental Health in College. Monthly reports included in the Administrative Records furnish clinical statistics on the numbers and types of cases and diagnoses of student patients in the aggregate, a good source for the student of the history of psychiatric diagnoses and nomenclature.
There are no case files among the records. All references to individual patients in correspondence were edited prior to being transferred to the archives. While detailed descriptions of various psychological disorders exist in reports and correspondence, they are largely absent.
Biographical / Historical
The Student Mental Hygiene Division of the Department of University Health was established at Yale in 1925 under President James Rowland Angell. The division began as a consulting body under Dr. Arthur Ruggles in effort to provide mental health and psychological services to Yale students, and found its more formal existence after 1930. Led by Dr. Clements Collard Fry, the office functioned to serve the needs of Yale students and faculty, assist the New Haven community, and was a leading advocate in the field of college mental hygiene. In addition to providing counseling and performing psychological testing, the division held courses, seminars, and lectures, engaged in special projects with outside bodies, including the U.S. government, and produced written reports based on its research.
Biographical / Historical
The Division of Student Mental Hygiene was launched in October 1925 when Dr. Arthur Ruggles was appointed consultant to the Yale Department of University Health and lecturer in psychiatry at the School of Medicine. The program began with strong ties to the medical school but functioned to serve the university community and surrounding city as well. In 1926 Ruggles left the position but continued to serve on the advisory committee; that same year a five-year program to develop a mental hygiene and psychiatry program was initiated through funding from the Commonwealth Fund. For the next five years the professional staff consisted of four psychiatrists and two social workers, headed by a chairman of administration and a clinical chief-of-staff who supervised work with students. During this period Dr. Clements Collard Fry became a clinical instructor for the department, and soon became very active in its administrative and research functions, later serving as a psychiatrist and eventually as chief psychiatrist. In 1930 the division offices were moved from the medical school to the Department of University Health, making services more accessible to students and enabling psychiatrists to work more closely with student health physicians, raising awareness and tolerance of psychiatry as a normal part of medical service. Most often students were referred to the clinic by student health physicians, deans, and faculty, but occasionally students sought the division's services on their own initiative.
Over the years the division offered programs that included public lectures, university courses taught by the chief psychiatrist, discussion groups on special topics, freshman seminars, and mental hygiene exams for all entering students from 1928 to 1932. The last program was later abandoned when it appeared that the results did not justify the amount of work or the monetary expense involved. A psychologist and two psychiatric social workers were added to the staff in the late 1920s. Early on, the psychologist was responsible for testing intelligence and aptitudes, and later counseled students, pursued research, and offered remedial reading programs. Social workers conducted preliminary interviews of students as part of routine mental hygiene exams and investigated the family and social histories of students who received treatment from the division. In 1932 when the budget and staff size were reduced, Dr. Catharine Miles of the Institute of Human Relations tested students in the absence of a staff psychologist.
By 1932, the division was fully established in the Yale community, but the staff and budget had dwindled considerably. The 1934 staff consisted of one psychiatrist, Dr. Clements Collard Fry, and a secretary, the former eventually becoming chief psychiatrist and responsible for directing the division's activities. The division began to evaluate its progress in 1935, with grant support from the Yale Institute of Human Relations and Paul Mellon. The evaluation resulted in the 1942 publication of Mental Health in College, a textexploring and classifying the psychological problems of Yale student patients. Informal orientation counseling had been initiated in the 1930s to help students adjust to the Yale environment, as well as remedial reading and study habit programs for freshmen. Both programs ceased to exist after 1950. After 1935 there was a steady increase in demand for the division's services and another Mellon grant in 1939 supported the hiring of assistant psychiatrist Dr. Lewis Thorne and full time psychologist Dr. Elden Bond.
Just as the clinical operations of the division were expanding, Dr. Thorne and Dr. Bond were called away to military service at the outbreak of World War II. During the war years the division was involved in research supporting the needs of the Surgeon General's Office and the Selective Service System. In 1943 a contract was signed between the National Research Council's Office of Scientific Research and Development and the Mental Hygiene Division that provided for investigation of psychiatric problems arising from military service. This contract was terminated in 1945. Project support was continued by the Surgeon General's office until 1950, and further investigation was then funded by the War Department. The studies conducted under these contracts analyzed the military experiences of 1,198 former patients of the Yale Division of Student Mental Hygiene and 819 patients of the Harvard Clinic. Study topics included case histories, suitability for service, psychiatric discharge rates, and adjustment to the military environment. The findings raised fundamental questions about then-current theories of military selection and produced six reports, including interim reports regarding homosexuality, psychoneuroses, and psychopathic personalities.
The student caseload doubled after the war. To help with the increased demand, philanthropist Paul Mellon contributed $25,000 per year from 1946 to 1949. This grant made it possible for the division to add staff, continue psychological services, participate in national and international conferences, and widen its consultative and educational activities. As interest in student mental health grew in academic institutions and among foundations nationwide, committees and professional organizations quickly multiplied. The division found itself receiving requests for advice from other universities and hosting physicians from all over the world. Dr. Thorne was able to resume his position as assistant psychiatrist in 1946, and two part-time psychiatrists, two full-time psychologists, and one part-time psychologist also joined the staff between 1946 and 1949. During this time an anthropologist also spent a year with the division studying the college environment.
At the same time the division was able to emphasize its long-standing commitment to research and examination of clinical training. A program of staff training was instituted, with seminars and discussions attended by members of other groups within the university. The division also cooperated with the Psychiatry Department of the medical school and the state of Connecticut to finance a post-graduate course on neurology and psychiatry for physicians, nurses, and social workers. The division participated in a survey of psychiatrists working in universities, and a round table meeting on college mental hygiene was held at the annual conference of the American Psychiatric Association. In 1949, the Old Dominion Fund through Paul Mellon endowed a gift of two million dollars to support the division's efforts. The gift supported the division's activities for almost two decades. In October 1950, Dr. Thorne was shot to death by a former patient. Three years later, a memorial library was dedicated in his honor at the Timothy Dwight Residence College. In 1951 the Divison issued "Retrospect and Prospect: A Special Report on the Twenty-Fifth Anniversary of the Student Mental Hygiene Service at Yale," a detailed reportand self-analysis summarizing its past efforts and involvements. Dr. Fry died in 1955, leaving Dr. Bryant M. Wedge to take his place as chief psychiatrist. Although there are no records beyond 1969, the division continues to operate today under the same name and department.
References:
Clements C. Fry and Edna G. Rostow. "Retrospect and Prospect: A Special Report on the Twenty-fifth Anniversary of the Student Mental Hygiene Service at Yale." Yale University: June 1951.
College students -- Mental health services; College students -- Mental health; Homosexuality; Mental health services; Psychoanalysis and homosexuality; Soldiers -- Mental health; Universities and colleges -- Health promotion services; World War, 1939-1945 -- Psychological aspects; United States -- Armed Forces -- Recruiting, enlistment, etc.; Fry, Clements Collard, 1892-1955; Kinsey, Alfred C. (Alfred Charles), 1894-1956; Raymond, Alice F.; Harvard University ( Students); National Research Council (U.S.); United States. Selective Service System; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Dept. of University Health
- Administrative Records, 1926-1969; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Administrative Records, is arranged under four sections: General Administrative Records, Financial Records, Monthly Reports, and Personnel.
  - General administration
    - Advisory board, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Department description, personnel, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Clements C. Fry seminar, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Forms for monthly reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Instructions to personnel, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Office equipment inventory, 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mary Mellon Institute for the Study of the Young Adult, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Organization charts, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Record keeping, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Reports of social service workers, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Financial records
    - Budget, 1950-1960
      General
      See: Restricted, 1949-1969 Folder 1
    - Commonwealth Fund, 1927-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11 - 12)
    - Old Dominion Fund
      - Mellon Grant announcement [becomes Old Dominion Fund], 1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Mellon Grant correspondence with university administration, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Early administrative correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Treasurer's office correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Monthly expense summaries
        - 1949-1957 (Box 2, Folder 17 - 24)
        - 1957-1966 (Box 3, Folder 25 - 33)
        - 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 34 - 36)
      - Payroll, 1949-1969
        General note
        See: Restricted, 1949-1969 Folder 2 - 3
    - Fundraising plans, 1940-1945 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Special Gift Fund account records, 1946-1960 (Box 4, Folder 38 - 43)
  - Monthly reports and clinical statistics
    - Clinical reports, 1926-1928 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Freshman conferences, 1926-1928 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Graphs of case-load files[compiled by A. Frank], 1950-1957 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Information for annual report, 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Monthly reports
      - 1926-1933 (Box 5, Folder 48 - 54)
      - 1933-1954 (Box 6, Folder 55 - 75)
    - Statistics on 265 students, 1926-1930 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Personnel
    - General, 1943-1949 (Box 7, Folder 77)
    - Applications and correspondence, 1927-1930 (Box 7, Folder 78)
    - Assistant psychiatrist, 1938-1942 (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - Division personnel, 1930-1933 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - Foreign personnel considered, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Prospective personnel, 1945-1949 (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Psychologists, 1945-1948 (Box 7, Folder 83)
- General Files and Correspondence, 1926-1964; Series II
  Arranged alphabetically, Series II is primarily composed of correspondence files, but also contains organizational, topical, and personal materials, the majority coming from the Fry administration. The existence of a designated correspondence folder for an individual or organization does not exclude the possibility that there are other pieces of correspondence to or from that individual or organization in the alphabetical file. The correspondence files document the whole range of activities and professional issues encountered by the Division of Student Mental Hygiene. Organizational files also contain pamphlets, conference and committee proceedings, agendas, and related planning materials. Topical and personal files include research reports, studies, article manuscripts, and proposals.
  - A [general], 1927-1957 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Advanced Mental Hygiene Course [Frankwood E. Williams' Lecture Course], 1928-1929 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Alcohol studies, [various studies by Lawrence K. Frank for National Research Council], 1947-1950 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Alcoholism, 1944-1959 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Aldrich, Knight, 1935-1955 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - American Association of Mental Hygiene Executives, 1930-1931 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - American Psychiatric Association
    - Committee on Academic Education, Clements C. Fry, 1952-1955 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Committee on History of Psychiatry, 1941-1944 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Appraisal of Mental Health in College Students as a Research Problem," by Lawrence K. Frank, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Army Medical Service Graduate School, Frank L.Bauer, 1951-1955 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - B [general], 1927-1955 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Binger report, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Board of admissions, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Boy Scout Manual, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Brain abscess [personal narrative by Lawrence B. Bixby], 1950 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 15
  - Bridgeport Community Chest and Council, 1930-1931 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Brooks, Ernest Jr. [Old Dominion Fund], 1947-1954 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    See also: Series I. Administrative Records, 1926-1969
  - C [general], 1927-1949 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Cheating, 1938-1951 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Child Study Association, 1930-1931 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Clinical pychologists, 1940-1951 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Committee on plans for research, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Committee on Student Health, 1938-1940 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Commonwealth Fund [correspondence re: Mental Health in College ], 1941-1943 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    See also: Series II. General Files and Correspondence, 1926-1964 Folder 86
  - Community prospects, 1928-1929 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Conduct irregularities, undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Connecticut Association for Mental Health, Psychiatric Advisory Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene, 1929-1940 (Box 9, Folder 29 - 31)
  - Connecticut Society for Psychiatry and Neurology, Chairman of Program Committee, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Connecticut State Medical Society, Sesquicentennial Celebration of 1942, 1941-1949 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Courses in Mental Hygiene, Undergraduate of Medical School, 1928-1930 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - D [general], 1929-1948 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Darling, George B. [letters], 1945-1952 (Box 10, Folder 36 - 37)
  - Deafness [transcript of Clements C. Fry interview by Paul MacCready], undated (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - DeVane, William C. [dean of Yale College], 1946 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Donors, letters to, 1944-1957 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - E [general], 1927-1947 (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Emery, Edgar V., [appointment of assistant professor of psychiatry], 1929 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - F [general], 1934-1948 (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - First International Congress on Mental Hygiene, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - "Foundations' Fund for Research in Psychiatry" [first annual report], 1954-1958 (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Fourth National Conference on Health in Colleges, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 46 - 47)
  - Frank, Lawrence K.
    See: Series II. General Files and Correspondence, 1926-1964 Folder 3 See: Series II. General Files and Correspondence, 1926-1964 Folder 10 See: Series II. General Files and Correspondence, 1926-1964 Folder 115
  - Fry estate, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 48)
  - Fry Memorial [materials for biography], 1941-1960 (Box 11, Folder 49)
  - G [general], 1926-1947 (Box 11, Folder 50)
  - Goldfarb, Alvin I., 1946-1949 (Box 11, Folder 51)
  - Graham, Billy [newsclippings], 1957 (Box 11, Folder 52)
  - Group psychotherapy, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 53)
  - Gundelfinger, George F. [publications by], 1936-1948 (Box 11, Folder 54)
  - H [general], 1931-1949 (Box 11, Folder 55)
  - Homosexuality, 1945-1952 (Box 11, Folder 56)
    See also: Series II. General Files and Correspondence, 1926-1964 Folder 69 See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 30 See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 48 See also: Series III. Project Files, 1929-1956 Folder 29
  - Hospital care of students, 1947-1958 (Box 11, Folder 57)
  - Hull's [Clark L.] informal seminars (Psych 106), 1936-1938 (Box 11, Folder 58)
  - Human relations in industry [Industrial Committee of Institute of Human Relations], 1930 (Box 11, Folder 59)
  - I [general], 1935-1941 (Box 11, Folder 60)
  - Insecurity case meetings, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 61)
  - Institute of Human Relations, 1929-1930 (Box 11, Folder 62)
  - International Congress on Mental Health, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 63)
  - International Student Service, 1940-1949 (Box 11, Folder 64)
  - J [general], 1945-1946 (Box 12, Folder 65)
  - Jung Institute (C. J. Jung Institute), 1951-1954 (Box 12, Folder 66)
  - K [general], 1930-1948 (Box 12, Folder 67)
  - Kahn, Eugen, 1929-1946 (Box 12, Folder 68)
  - Kinsey, Alfred C. [responses to Kinsey Report], 1946-1948 (Box 12, Folder 69)
  - Koppelman, Samuel, 1940-1941 (Box 12, Folder 70)
  - Kubie, Lawrence S., 1946-1950 (Box 12, Folder 71)
  - L [general], 1931-1948 (Box 12, Folder 72)
  - Leavy, Stanley A., 1949-1950 (Box 12, Folder 73)
  - Lecturers, 1946-1947 (Box 12, Folder 74)
  - Lectures, 1946-1947 (Box 12, Folder 75)
  - Levy, David M., 1947-1954 (Box 12, Folder 76)
  - M [general], 1927-1948 (Box 12, Folder 77)
  - Maclay, Walter S., 1944-1953 (Box 12, Folder 78)
  - Massachusetts Society for Mental Hygiene, "Keeping Mentally Fit" [course materials], 1930-1931 (Box 12, Folder 79)
  - May, Mark [regarding Mental Health in College ], 1937-1940 (Box 12, Folder 80)
  - McDowell, John H., 1937 (Box 13, Folder 81)
  - Medical school applicants, 1934-1938 (Box 13, Folder 82)
  - Menninger, William C. Karl, 1947-1953 (Box 13, Folder 83)
  - Menninger Foundation, 1947-1948 (Box 13, Folder 84)
  - Mental disease compared with cancer, polio, tuberculosis [research data from United States Public Health], 1948-1953 (Box 13, Folder 85)
  - Mental Health in College [1942]
    - Comments, 1942-1945 (Box 13, Folder 86)
    - Data used, 1930-1934 (Box 13, Folder 87)
  - "Mental Hygiene and Education," [report by C. Macfie Campbell], Circa 1927 (Box 13, Folder 88)
  - Michigan State College, 1942-1955 (Box 13, Folder 89)
  - Miles, Catharine [Institute of Human Relations], 1938-1940 (Box 13, Folder 90)
  - Morris, Newbold [letters to son regarding sexuality], 1940 (Box 13, Folder 91)
  - N [general], 1941-1949 (Box 13, Folder 92)
  - National Academy of Sciences, Symposium on Selection of Manpower, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 93)
  - National Association for Mental Health, 1949-1952 (Box 13, Folder 94 - 95)
  - National Committee for Mental Hygiene, 1929-1942 (Box 13, Folder 96 - 97)
  - National Institute of Mental Health, 1948-1951 (Box 14, Folder 98)
  - National Mental Health Act [proposals to Congress], 1946-1947 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  - National Mental Health Committee, 1949-1953 (Box 14, Folder 100)
  - Neuropsychiatrics Anonymous, 1946-1947 (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - New England Conference on Mental Hygiene in Education, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - New Haven Home, 1930 (Box 14, Folder 103)
  - Nudism [Post Office complaint], 1947 (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - O [general], 1932-1949 (Box 14, Folder 105)
  - P [general], 1931-1949 (Box 14, Folder 106)
  - Pappenheim, Else, 1946-1949 (Box 14, Folder 107)
  - Pasternak, Maxwell, 1948 (Box 14, Folder 108)
  - Perry, Doris E., 1931 (Box 14, Folder 109)
  - "Personality and Higher Education" [study at Vassar College], 1946-1964 (Box 14, Folder 110)
  - Pittsburgh Community Program, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 111)
  - Pratt, Dallas, 1935-1954 (Box 14, Folder 112)